I have 18 minutes to tell you what happened
لدي 18 دقيقة لأخبركم ماذا حدث
over the past six million years.
عبر الست ملايين سنة الماضية.
All right.
حسناً.
We all have come from a long way,
لقد أتينا جميعاً من طريق بعيد،
here in Africa, and converged in this region of Africa,
هنا في أفريقيا، وتلتقي في هذه المنطقة من أفريقيا،
which is a place where 90 percent of our evolutionary process took place.
الذي هو المكان الذي حدثت فيه 90 بالمائة من عملية تطورنا.
And I say that not because I am African,
وأنا اقول ذلك ليس لأنني أفريقي،
but it's in Africa that you find the earliest evidence
لكن في أفريقيا تجد أقدم الأدلة
for human ancestors, upright walking traces,
لأسلاف البشر، آثار المشي واقفين،
even the first technologies in the form of stone tools.
وحتى أول التكنلوجيات في شكل أدوات حجرية.
So we all are Africans, and welcome home.
إذاً فنحن جميعنا أفارقة، ومرحباً بكم في الوطن.
All right.
حسناً.
I'm a paleoanthropologist, and my job is to define
أنا عالم حفريات أنثروبولوجي، ومهمتي هي التعرف
man's place in nature and explore what makes us human.
على مكان البشر في الطبيعة وإستكشاف ما يجعلنا بشراً،
And today, I will use Selam, the earliest child ever discovered,
واليوم سأستخدم سلام، أول طفل تم العثور عليه،
to tell you a story of all of us.
لأخبركم بقصة لنا جميعاً.
Selam is our most complete skeleton of a three-year-old girl
سلام هي أول هيكل كامل لنا لطفلة عمرها ثلاث سنوات
who lived and died 3.3 million years ago.
التي عاشت وماتت قبل 3.3 مليون سنة مضت.
She belongs to the species known as Australopithecus afarensis.
وهي تنتمي لنوع معروف ب أسترالوبيثكس أفارينسيس.
You don't need to remember that.
لن تحتاجوا لتذكر ذلك.
That's the Lucy species, and was found by my research team
تلك أنواع لوسي، وقد عثر عليها فريقي البحثي
in December of 2000 in an area called Dikika.
في ديسمبر عام 2000 في منطقة تسمى ديكيكا.
It's in the northeastern part of Ethiopia.
وهي في الجزء الشمالي الشرقي لأثيوبيا.
And Selam means peace in many Ethiopian languages.
وسلام تعني السلام في العديد من اللغات الأثيوبية.
We use that name to celebrate peace in the region and in the planet.
ونحن نستخدم الأسم للإحتفاء بالسلام في المنطقة وفي الكوكب.
And the fact that it was the cover story of all these famous magazines
و حقيقة أنها كانت موضوع الغلاف لكل هذه المجلات المشهورة
gives you already an idea of her significance, I think.
يعطيكم فكرة بالفعل حول أهميتها، كما أعتقد.
After I was invited by TED, I did some digging,
وبعد أن تمت دعوتي لتيد، قمت ببعض التدقيق،
because that's what we do, to know about my host.
لأن ذلك ما نفعله، لأعرف عن مضيفي.
You don't just jump into an invitation.
لا تقوم فقط بإستجابة الدعوة.
And I learned that the first technology appeared
وقد علمت أن أول تكنلوجيا ظهرت
in the form of stone tools, 2.6 million years ago.
في شكل أدوات حجرية كان قبل 2.6 مليون سنة مضت.
First entertainment comes evidence from flutes that are 35,000 years old.
أول دلائل الترفيه تأتي كدليل من مزامير عمرها 35،000 سنة.
And evidence for first design comes 75,000 years old -- beads.
والدليل على أول تصميم يأتي من خرز عمره 75،000 سنة.
And you can do the same with your genes and track them back in time.
ويمكنك فعل نفس الشئ مع جيناتك وتتبعها عبر الزمن.
And DNA analysis of living humans and chimpanzees
ثم التحليل للبشر الأحياء والشمبانزي
teaches us today that we diverged sometime around seven million years ago
يعلمنا اليوم أننا تقاربنا في وقت ما حوالي قبل سبعة ملايين سنة مضت
and that these two species share over 98 percent of the same genetic material.
وأن هذه الكائنات تتشارك ما يزيد على 98 في المائة من نفس المواد الجينية.
I think knowing this is a very useful context
أعتقد أن معرفة هذا مفيد للغاية في سياق
within which we can think of our ancestry.
الذي فيه يمكننا التفكير بأسلافنا.
However, DNA analysis informs us only about
لكن، يعلمنا التحليل فقط حول
the beginning and the end, telling us nothing
البداية والنهاية، ولا يخبرنا بشئ
about what happened in the middle.
حول ماذا حدث في المنتصف.
So, for us, paleoanthropologists, our job is to find the hard evidence,
لذا فالنسبة لنا كعلماء حفريات أنثروبولجيا تدور مهمتنا في إيجاد دليل قوي،
the fossil evidence, to fill in this gap
لأدلة الحفريات، لملئ هذا الفراغ
and see the different stages of development.
ومعرفة المراحل المختلفة للتطور.
Because it's only when you do that, that you can talk about --
لأنه فقط عندما تفعل ذلك يمكنك الحديث عن
(Laughter) --
كيف كنا نبدو وكيف تصرفنا في أوقات مختلفة،
it's only when you do that, [that] you can talk about
وكيف أن ذلك الشبه والسلوك قد تغير عبر الزمن،
how we looked like and how we behaved at different times,
ثم يعطينا وسيلة
and how those likes and looks and behaviors changed through time.
لإستكشاف الآليات البيولوجية
That then gives you an access
والقوى المسؤلة من هذا التغيير التدريجي
to explore the biological mechanisms
الذي جعلنا على ما نحن عليه اليوم.
and forces that are responsible for this gradual change
لكن العثور على أدلة دامغة هو مسعى معقد للغاية.
that made us what we are today.
إنها مقاربة منهجية وعلمية،
But finding the hard evidence is a very complicated endeavor.
التي تأخذك وتضعك في أماكن بعيدة، حارة وفي العادة بدون وسائل إتصال.
It's a systematic and scientific approach,
فقط لأعطيكم مثالاً، عندما ذهبت إلى ديكيكا،
which takes you to places that are remote, hot, hostile and often with no access.
حيث عُثر على سلام، عام 99، لقد كانت على بعد 500 كيلومتراً
Just to give you an example, when I went to Dikika,
من أديس أبابا، عاصمة أثيوبيا.
where Selam was found, in '99 -- and it's about 500 kilometers
لقد أستغرت الوصول لأول 470 كيلومتراً فقط سبع ساعات من ال500،
from Addis Ababa, the capital of Ethiopia.
لكن أستغرق أربع ساعات صعبة لبحث ال30 كليومتراً الأخيرة.
It took us only seven hours to do the first 470 kilometers of the 500,
بمساعدة السكان المحليين وبإستخدام المعاول والنشل، تمكنت من الوصول.
but took four, solid hours to do the last only 30 kilometers.
لقد كنت أول شخص يقود سيارة إلى الموقع.
With the help of the locals and using just shovels and picks, I made my way.
عندما تصل إلى هناك، هذا ما ستراه،
I was the first person to actually drive a car to the spot.
وإنه لمكان متسع الشئ الذي يجعلك تشعر بالضعف والعجز.
When you get there, this is what you see,
وبمجرد وصولك إلى هناك، فالسؤال الأكبر هو من أين نبدأ.
and it's the vastness of the place which makes you feel helpless and vulnerable.
لا تعثر على شئ لسنوات وسنوات.
And once you make it there, the big question is where to start.
وعندما أذهب لأماكن مثل هذه، التي هي مواقع للحفريات،
(Laughter)
فالأمر مثل الذهاب لحديقة ألعاب، حديقة ألعاب منقرضة.
And you find nothing for years and years.
لكن ما نجده ليس بقايا بشرية،
When I go to places like this, which are paleontological sites,
مثل سلام أو لوسي، بمعدل يومي.
it's like going to a game park, an extinct game park.
نجد فيلة، وحيد القرن، قرود، خنازير، وهلمجرا.
But what you find are not the human remains,
لكن يمكنك السؤال، كيف أمكن هذه الثديات الضخمة
such as Selam and Lucy, on a day-to-day basis.
أن تعيش في بيئة صحراوية؟
You find elephants, rhinos, monkeys, pigs, etc.
بالطبع لا تستطيع ذلك، لكن أنا أخبركم بالفعل
But you could ask, how could these large mammals
بأن البيئة والطاقة الإستيعابية
live in this desert environment?
لهذه المنطقة كانت مختلفة جذرياً مما هي عليه اليوم.
Of course, they cannot, but I'm telling you already
وهو الدرس البيئي المهم الذي يمكن تعلمه من هذا.
that the environment and the carrying capacity
على أي حال، بمجرد وصولنا، فالأمر مثل منتزه الألعاب، كما قلت-- حديقة حيوانات منقرضة.
of this region was drastically different from what we have today.
وقد عاش أسلافنا في منتزه الألعاب ذلك،
A very important environmental lesson could be learned from this.
لكنهم كانوا أقليات. لم يكونوا ناجحين
Anyway, once we made it there, then it's a game park, as I said, an extinct game park.
ومنتشرين كما هو حال الهومو سبينس(الإنسان العاقل) التي عليها نحن الآن.
And our ancestors lived in that game park,
لأقدم لكم مثالاً، قصة عن مدى ندرتهم،
but were just the minorities. They were not as successful
كنت أذهب لهذا المكان سنوياً وأقوم بالعمل الميداني هنا،
and as widespread as the Homo sapiens that we are.
والمساعدين، بالطبع ساعدوني لإنجاز المسوحات.
To tell you just an example, an anecdote about their rarity,
يجدون العظم ويخبروني، " ها هو ما تبحث عنه."
I was going to this place every year and would do fieldwork here,
وأقول، " لا ذلك فيل."
and the assistants, of course, helped me do the surveys.
مجدداً، شئ آخر --" ذلك قرد،" " ذلك خنزير،" وهلمجرا.
They would find a bone and tell me, "Here is what you're looking for."
حتى قال أحد المساعدين، الذين لم يتلقوا تعليماً قط، " أسمع، زيراي.
I would say, "No, that's an elephant."
إمّا أنك لا تعرف ما تبحث عنه،
Again, another one, "That's a monkey." "That's a pig," etc.
أو أنك تبحث في المكان الخطأ،" كما قال.
So one of my assistants, who never went to school, said to me, "Listen, Zeray.
وقد قلت، " لماذا؟" رد " لأن هناك أفيال وأسود،
You either don't know what you're looking for,
وكان الناس خائفون وذهبوا لمكان آخر.
or you're looking in the wrong place," he said.
لنذهب لمكان آخر."
(Laughter)
حسناً، لقد كان متعباً للغاية، والأمر حقاً متعب.
And I said, "Why?" "Because there were elephants and lions,
كان حينها بعد عمل شاق والعديد من السنوات المحبطة حتى وجدنا سلام،
and the people were scared and went somewhere else.
وأنتم ترون الوجه هنا مغطى بالحجر الرملي.
Let's go somewhere else."
وهنا في الواقع العمود الفقري
Well, he was very tired, and it's really tiring.
والجذع كله مغطى في كتلة من الحجر الرملي،
It was then, after such hard work and many frustrating years that we found Selam,
وذلك لأنها كانت مدفونة قرب النهر.
and you see the face here covered by sandstone.
ما حصلتم عليه هو يبدو لا شئ،
And here is actually the spinal column
لكنه يحوي كمية مأهولة من البيانات العلمية
and the whole torso encased in a sandstone block,
التي تساعدنا في إستكشاف ما يجعلنا بشراً.
because she was buried by a river.
هذا هو أول وأكمل سلف للإنسان الحديث
What you have here seems to be nothing,
تم العثور عليه في تاريخ حفريات الأنثروبولوجيا --
but contains an incredible amount of scientific information
قطعة رائعة لتاريخنا الطويل جداً.
that helps us explore what makes us human.
كان هناك ثلاثة أشخاص وأنا، وأنا ألتقط الصور،
This is the earliest and most complete juvenile human ancestor
لهذا أنا لست فيها.
ever found in the history of paleoanthropology,
كيف كنت لتشعر إن كنت مكاني، لديك شئ إستثنائي بين يديك،
an amazing piece of our long, long history.
لكنك وسط اللاشئ؟
There were these three people and me, and I am taking the pictures,
الإحساس الذي تملكني كان عميقاً وسعادة بالغة وإثارة،
that's why I am not in.
بالطبع مصحوبة بإحساس كبير بالمسؤولية،
How would you feel if you were me? You have something extraordinary in your hand,
لأتأكد من أن كل شئ آمن.
but you are in the middle of nowhere?
ها هنا إغلاق الحفرية بعد خمس سنوات من التنظيف،
The feeling I had was a deep and quiet happiness and excitement,
التحضير، والوصف -- التي كانت طويلة للغاية،
of course accompanied by a huge sense of responsibility,
وتوجب عليّ الكشف على العظام من كتل الحجر الرملية
of making sure everything is safe.
التي عرضتها عليكم في الشريحة السابقة.
Here is a close-up of the fossil, after five years of cleaning,
أستغرقت خمس سنوات.
preparation and description, which was very long,
بشكل ما، كان هذا مثل ميلاد ثاني لطفلة بعد 3.3 مليون سنة،
as I had to expose the bones from the sandstone block
لكن العمل كان طويلاً للغاية.
I just showed you in the previous slide.
وها هنا الحجم الكامل -- إنها عظام صغيرة للغاية.
It took five years.
وفي المنتصف وزير السياحة الأثيوبية،
In a way, this was like the second birth for the child, after 3.3 million years,
الذي جاء لزيارة المتحف الوطني في أثيوبيا أثناء عملي هناك.
but the labor was very long.
ويمكنكم رؤيتي قلق ومحاولاً حماية طفلي،
And here is full scale -- it's a tiny bone.
لأنك لا تترك أي شخص مع هذا النوع من الأطفال،
And in the middle is the minister of Ethiopian tourism,
حتى الوزير.
who came to visit the National Museum of Ethiopia while I was working there.
إذاً فبمجرد إنتهاءك من ذلك، فالخطوة التالية هي معرفة ماهيتها.
And you see me worried and trying to protect my child,
بمجرد فراغك من ذلك، عندها من الممكن المقارنة.
because you don't leave anyone with this kind of child,
لقد أمكننا القول أنها تنتمي
even a minister.
لشجرة أسرة البشر بسبب رجليها، القدم،
So then, once you've done that, the next stage is to know what it is.
وبعض الصفات التي أوضحت بجلاء أنها مشت واقفة،
(Laughter)
والمشي وقوفاً هو علامة مميزة في الإنسان.
Once that was done, then it was possible to compare.
لكن إضافة لذلك، تقوم بمقارنة الجمجمة
We were able to tell that she belonged
مع شمبانزي وجورج بوش صغير هنا،
to the human family tree because the legs, the foot,
يمكنك رؤية أن هناك جبين عمودي،
and some features clearly showed that she walked upright,
ويمكنك رؤية ذلك في البشر، بفعل تطور
and upright walking is a hallmark in humanity.
القشرة قبل الجبهية، كما تسمى --
But in addition, if you compare the skull
لا تلاحظ ذلك في الشمبانزي،
with a comparably aged chimpanzee and little George Bush here,
ولا ترى هذه الأنياب الساقطة.
you see that you have vertical forehead.
إذاً فهي تنتمي لشجرتنا، لكن بالطبع أثناء ذلك،
And you see that in humans, because of the development
تقوم بتحليل تفصيلي ونعرف الآن
of the pre-frontal cortex, it's called.
أنها تنتمي إلى نوع لوسي،
You don't see that in chimpanzees,
المعروفة ك أسترالوبيثكس أفارنسيس.
and you don't see this very projecting canine.
السؤال المثير التالي هو هل ولد أم بنت،
So she belongs to our family tree, but within that, of course,
وكم عمرها عندما ماتت.
you do detailed analysis, and we know now
يمكنك تحديد جنس الشخص
that she belongs to the Lucy species,
بناء على الحجم والأسنان.
known as Australopithecus afarensis.
كيف؟
The next exciting question is, girl or boy?
كما تعلمون، في المقدمات، هناك هذه الظاهرة
And how old was she when she died?
التي تسمى إزدواج الشكل الجنسي، الذي يعني ببساطة
You can determine the sex of the individual
أن الذكور أضخم من الاناث وأن للذكور أسنان أكبر
based on the size of the teeth.
من الاناث.
How?
لكن لفعل ذلك، نحتاج لأسنان دائمة،
You know, in primates, there is this phenomenon
التي لا نراها هنا لأن ما لدينا هنا
called sexual dimorphism, which simply means
هي أسنان لطفلة.
males are larger than females and males have larger teeth
لكن بإستخدام تقنية المسح المقطعي ،
than the females.
والتي تستخدم عادة لأغراض طبية،
But to do that, you need the permanent dentition,
يمكنك التعمق في الفم وتحصل على هذه الصورة الجميلة
which you don't see here, because what you have here
التي تعرض لك كلا من أسنان الطفل هنا
are the baby teeth.
وسن ما يزال ينمو لبالغ هنا.
But using the CT scanning technology,
لذا فعندما نقيس تلك الأسنان،
which is normally used for medical purposes,
كان من الواضح أنها بدأت تتضح كانثى
you can go deep into the mouth and come up with this beautiful image
مع أنياب صغيرة للغاية.
showing you both the baby teeth here
ولمعرفة كم كان عمرها عندما ماتت، ما تحتاج لفعله هو
and the still-growing adult teeth here.
هو القيام بتقدير واعي وتقول لكم كم من الوقت سيلزم
So when you measure those teeth,
لتشكيل هذا العدد من الأسنان ، والإجابة كانت ثلاثة.
it was clear that she turned out to be a girl
إذاً فقد ماتت الطفلة عندما كانت حوالي ثلاثة،
with very small canine teeth.
3.3 ملايين سنة مضت.
And to know how old she was when she died, what you do is
إذاً مع كل هذه المعلومات، فأن السؤال الكبير هو --
you do an informed estimate, and you say, how much time would be required
بماذا تخبرنا في الواقع؟
to form this amount of teeth, and the answer was three.
ولإجابة هذا السؤال، يمكننا طرح سؤال آخر --
So, this girl died when she was about three,
ما الذي نعلمه بالفعل عن أسلافنا؟
3.3 million years ago.
نريد أن نعرف كيف كان شكلهم، سلوكهم،
So, with all that information, the big question is --
وكيف تنقلوا،
what do we actually -- what does she tell us?
وكيف عاشوا وترعرعوا.
To answer this question, we can phrase another question.
ومن بين الإجابات التي يمكنك الحصول عليها من هذا الهيكل
What do we actually know about our ancestors?
كلها مشمولة -- أولاً هذا الهيكل يوثق
We want to know how they looked like, how they behaved,
لأول مرة كيف بدى الأطفال قبل ثلاثة ملايين سنة مضت.
how they walked around,
وثانياً، تخبرنا بأنهم مشوا واقفين،
and how they lived and grew up.
لكن كان لديهم بعض التكيف لتسلق الأشجار.
And among the answers that you can get from this skeleton
ولكن الأكثر إثارة،
are included: first, this skeleton documents,
أن الدماغ عند هذه الطفلة كان ما يزال ينمو.
for the first time, how infants looked over three million years ago.
في سن الثالثة، إن كان لديك دماغ ما يزال ينمو،
And second, she tells us that she walked upright,
فهذا سلوك بشري.
but had some adaptation for tree climbing.
عند الشمبانزي، في عمر الثالثة، يكون 90 في المائة من الدماغ قد تشكّل.
And more interesting, however,
لهذا يستطيعون التكيف مع بيئاتهم
is the brain in this child was still growing.
بسهولة شديدة بعد الميلاد -- أسرع منا، على أي حال.
At age three, if you have a still-growing brain,
لكن البشر، نواصل نمو أدمغتنا.
it's a human behavior.
ولهذا نحتاج لرعاية من والدينا.
In chimps, by age three, the brain is formed over 90 percent.
لكن تلك الرعاية تعني أيضاً التعلم.
That's why they can cope with their environment
أنت تقضي وقتاً أكبر مع والديك.
very easily after birth -- faster than us, anyway.
وهذه خصائص بشرية جداً وتسمى الطفولة،
But in humans, we continue to grow our brains.
التي لها إعتمادية ممتدة للطفل البشري
That's why we need care from our parents.
على أسرهم أو والديهم.
But that care means also you learn.
إذاً فالدماغ الذي ينمو في هذا الشخص
You spend more time with your parents.
يخبرنا أن تلك الطفولة، التي تحتاج
And that's very characteristic of humans and it's called childhood,
لرعاية إجتماعية لا تصدق،
which is this extended dependence of human children
رعاية إجتماعية معقدة للغاية،
on their family or parents.
ظهرت لأكثر من ثلاثة ملايين سنة مضت.
So, the still-growing brain in this individual
ويجري ذلك على أعتاب تاريخنا التطوري،
tells us that childhood, which requires
توحدنا سلام وتعطينا صورة فريدة
an incredible social organization,
حول ما يجعلنا بشراً.
a very complex social organization,
لكن لم يكن كل شئ بشرياً، وسأعطيكم
emerged over three million years ago.
مثالاً مثيراً للغاية.
So, by being at the cusp of our evolutionary history,
يسمى هذا العظام اللامي. إنها العظام التي تقع هنا.
Selam unites us all and gives us a unique account
إنها تدعم اللسان من الخلف.
on what makes us human.
إنها بطريقة ما، علبة الصوت لدينا.
But not everything was human, and I will give you
إنها تحدد نوع الصوت الذي نصدره.
a very exciting example.
لم تكن معروفة في سجل الحفريات،
This is called the hyoid bone. It's a bone which is right here.
ولدينا في هذا الهيكل.
It supports your tongue from behind.
عندما قمنا بتحليل العظام، كان واضحاً
It's, in a way, your voice box.
إنها بدت تشبه الشمبانزي، مثل الشمبانزي.
It determines the type of voice you produce.
لذا إن كنت هناك قبل 3.3 ملايين سنة مضت،
It was not known in the fossil record,
لتسمع عندما تبكي هذه الفتاة لأمها،
and we have it in this skeleton.
لكان صوتها أقرب للشمبانزي من البشر.
When we did the analysis of this bone, it was clear
ربما تستغربون، " إذا ترون ميزة القرد هذه، ميزة البشر، القرد.
that it looked very chimp-like, chimpanzee-like.
بماذا يخبرنا ذلك؟"
So if you were there 3.3 million years ago,
كما تعلمون، هذا مثير للغاية بالنسبة لنا،
to hear when this girl was crying out for her mother,
لأنه يمهد لأن الأشياء كانت تتغير ببطء وتدريجياً،
she would have sounded more like a chimpanzee than a human.
وأن التطور في طور التشكيل.
Maybe you're wondering, "So, you see this ape feature, human feature, ape feature.
لتلخيص أهمية هذه الحفريات،
What does that tell us?"
يمكننا قول الآتي.
You know, that is very exciting for us,
حتى الآن، المعرفة التي لدينا حول أسلافنا
because it demonstrates that things were changing slowly and progressively,
تأتي في الأساس من الأشخاص البالغين
and that evolution is in the making.
بسبب الحفريات، حفريات الأطفال كان غائبة.
To summarize the significance of this fossil,
إنها لا تُحفظ جدياً، كما تعلمون.
we can say the following.
إذاً فالمعروفة التي لدينا حول أسلافنا
Up to now, the knowledge that we had about our ancestors
حول كيف كان شكلهم، كيف تصرفوا،
came essentially from adult individuals
كان متحيزاً نوعاً ما تجاه البالغين.
because the fossils, the baby fossils, were missing.
تخيلوا أن يأتيك شخص من كوكب المريخ
They don't preserve well, as you know.
وعمله هو الإبلاغ عن نوع الناس
So the knowledge that we had about our ancestors,
الذي يسكنون كوكبنا الأرض، ونقوم بإخفاء جميع الأطفال،
on how they looked like, how they behaved,
الصغار، ويرجع ليقوم بالإبلاغ.
was kind of biased toward adults.
هل تتخيلوا كم سيكون تقريره متحيز اً؟
Imagine somebody coming from Mars
ذلك ما كنا بطريقة ما نفعله
and his job is to report on the type of people
في ظل غياب حفريات الأطفال،
occupying our planet Earth, and you hide all the babies,
لذا فأنني أعتقد أن الحفرية الجديدة تحلّ هذه المشكلة.
the children, and he goes back and reports.
لذا أعتقد أن أهم الأسئلة في النهاية هي،
Can you imagine how much biased his report would be?
ماذا نتعلم فعلا من مثل هذه العينات
That's what somehow we were doing so far
من ماضينا وبشكل عام؟
in the absence of the fossil children,
بالطبع ، بالإضافة إلى استخراج هذه الكمية الهائلة
so I think the new fossil fixes this problem.
من المعلومات العلمية بشأن ما يجعلنا بشرا،
So, I think the most important question at the end is,
كما تعلمون ، أسلاف العديد من البشرية التي وجدت
what do we actually learn from specimens like this
خلال الست ملايين سنة الماضية -- وهناك أكثر من 10 --
and from our past in general?
لم يكن لديهم المعرفة، التقنية والتطور
Of course, in addition to extracting this huge amount
التي لدى الإنسان العاقل اليوم.
of scientific information as to what makes us human,
لكن إن كان هذا الإنسان القديم العاقل،
you know, the many human ancestors that have existed
سيسافر عبر الزمن ويرانا اليوم،
over the past six million years -- and there are more than 10 --
فأنه سيكون فخوراً جداً بتركته،
they did not have the knowledge, the technology and sophistications
لأنهم أصبحوا إسلافاً ل
that we, Homo sapiens, have today.
أكثر الكائنات نجاحاً في الكون.
But if this species, ancient species,
وعلى الأرجح أنهم لم يكونوا واعين لهذه التركة المستقبلية،
would travel in time and see us today,
لكنهم فعلوا حسناً.
they would very much be very proud of their legacy,
الآن السؤال هو، أننا الإنسان العاقل اليوم
because they became the ancestors of
في وضعية للتقرير حول مستقبل كوكبنا، وربما أكثر.
the most successful species in the universe.
إذاً فالسؤال هو، هل في مستوى التحدي؟
And they were probably not aware of this future legacy,
ويمكن أن نفعل أفضل من تلك العقول،
but they did great.
الصغيرة البدائية للأسلاف؟
Now the question is, we Homo sapiens today
من بين التحديات الضاغطة للغاية على نوعنا
are in a position to decide about the future of our planet, possibly more.
التي تواجهنا اليوم هي المشكلة المزمنة لأفريقيا.
So the question is, are we up to the challenge?
لا حاجة لإدراجهم هنا، وهناك أناس أفضل
And can we really do better than these primitive,
للحديث حول هذا.
small-brained ancestors?
يظل في نظري، ان لدينا خيارين.
Among the most pressing challenges that our species
أحدها هو مواصلة رؤية أفريقيا الفقيرة المريضة الباكية،
is faced with today are the chronic problems of Africa.
تحمل السلاح وتعتمد على الآخرين إلى الأبد،
Needless to list them here, and there are more competent people
أو أن نروّج لأفريقيا واثقة،
to talk about this.
مسالمة، مستقلة، لكن يجب إدراك مشاكلها الضخمة
Still, in my opinion, we have two choices.
والقيم العظيمة في نفس الوقت.
One is to continue to see a poor, ill, crying Africa,
أنا أدعم الخيار الثاني، وأنا متأكد أن العديدين منكم كذلك.
carrying guns, that depends on other people forever,
والمفتاح هو الترويج لسلوك أفريقي إيجابي تجاه أفريقيا.
or to promote an Africa which is confident,
وذلك لأننا كأفارقة نركز --
peaceful, independent, but cognizant of its huge problems
أنا من أثيوبيا بالمناسبة --
and great values at the same time.
نركز كثيراً على كيف يرانا
I am for the second option, and I'm sure many of you are.
الآخرون من الخارج.
And the key is to promote a positive African attitude towards Africa.
أعتقد أنه من المهم الترويج بصورة أكثر إيجابية
That's because we Africans concentrate --
حول كيف نرى أنفسنا.
I am from Ethiopia, by the way --
هذا ما أسميه سلوك أفريقي إيجابي.
we concentrate too much on how we are seen
لذا في الختام، أرغب بالقول،
from elsewhere, or from outside.
لنساعد أفريقيا في المسير واقفة وإلى الأمام --
I think it's important to promote in a more positive way
عندئذ يمكننا الفخر بتركتنا المستقبلية كأنواع.
on how we see ourselves.
شكراً لكم.
That's what I call positive African attitude.
(تصفيق)